This package is just leaving a warehouse
in China. It's roughly 15 by 20 cm in
size and about a kilo in weight. The
label says dog food, but inside is a
fine white powder. It's the core
ingredient for one of the deadliest
drugs in the world, fentinyl. Cheaper
than heroin and about 50 times as
strong. An amount this small is enough
to kill you. In the US, fentinyl has
become the number one source of death
for adults under 50, surpassing cancer,
heart disease, and car accidents. How
can its ingredients just move freely
across continents, shipped, sorted, and
delivered like an ordinary online order?
Behind it lies a billiondoll system run
by cartels, fueled by global trade, and
enabled by broken regulations. A deadly
supply chain hiding in plain sight. This
is how fentinyl is trafficked.
[Music]
>> If you or someone you know is struggling
with substance use, help us out there.
Visit findtreatment.gov for support in
the US or check these platforms to find
international resources near you. All
links are in the description. Also, this
video is partly based on this incredible
Reuters investigation. You'll find the
link in the description as well.
This is fentinyl. It's been used in
medicine since the 1960s, mostly as a
painkiller. Today, it's also applied as
an anesthetic. Its effect is insanely
strong, around 100 times more potent
than morphine and 50 times stronger than
heroin. It's also extremely addictive.
Over the last 15 years, the illegal
fentinel trade in the US has fueled an
unprecedented synthetic opioid crisis.
and the impact can be seen across the
entire country. The biggest problem is
that the substance is highly lethal. The
number of deaths by fentinyl overdose in
the US has exploded over the last few
years. About 75,000 people died in 2023
alone. In total, fentinyl and other
synthetic opioids have killed nearly
half a million Americans between 1999
and 2022. One reason for this death toll
is a process called lacing. Dealers
consciously mix fentinyl into other
street drugs like heroin to stretch
supplies and boost their profits. A
little fentinyl goes a long way, but
that also means users get hooked faster
and are much more likely to overdose not
knowing what they are consuming. For
those who traffic it, fentinyl has
another major upside. It's synthetic.
That means it's incredibly cheap and
easy to produce. The business is so
profitable that Mexican cartels have
massively shifted to fentinil over the
last few years. Instead of cultivating
huge poppy fields for heroin, they can
simply fabricate the drug in a lab,
receiving the base ingredients by mail.
Most of the packages moving down the
conveyor belts in China are carrying
everyday goods, chargers, clothes, dog
food. But hidden among those thousands
of boxes are the ingredients for
fentinel. This little box is just one of
countless packages going out of China
every day. For efficient transportation,
shipping companies bundle individual
packages into what's known as a master
carton. Master cartons are a cornerstone
of global trade. Shipping one big box is
cheaper and much more efficient than
sending numerous small ones to the same
destination. The master cartons are then
stacked onto pallets with other bug
shipments and the tiny fentinel
precursor package ends up tucked deep
inside. Then the master cartons are
often loaded onto a plane and flown to
their real destination, the United
States.
There's something about taking flight,
getting that bird's eye view, seeing how
small details connect to a much bigger
system. Perspective matters. Whether
you're trying to understand global
trade, piece together a true crime
story, or really understand a complex
idea, you need to look at things from
different angles, that's what Brilliant
helps you to do. The hands-on learning
platform helps you become a better
thinker with thousands of interactive
lessons in math, science, data analysis,
AI, and more. Whether you want to
understand how algorithms work, start
coding, or build sharper logical
thinking, the courses on Brilliant start
with the foundations and guide you step
by step toward focused and meaningful
learning. For example, they've got a
great course on logic that helps you
stretch your analytic muscles. You're
connecting dots, drawing conclusions,
and thinking clearly under pressure. You
solve puzzles using limited clues, break
codes, and even train logical robots.
It's hands-on brain stretching stuff.
Head to brilliant.org/varn and try
everything Brilliant has to offer for a
full 30 days. Use this QR code or the
link in the description to get 20% off
an annual premium subscription.
Global online shopping has seen a
massive boom in recent years. Fentinel
smugglers are riding that wave by
sneaking their products into the vast
international shipping stream and
they're exploiting one particular
loophole in the US. Back in the 1930s,
Washington introduced a special customs
regulation called the minimese. If a
package is addressed to a private person
and the goods inside are below a certain
value, it skips costumes entirely. That
means there are no duties and almost no
detailed checks. Many countries have
similar policies. In the European Union,
the cutoff is €150.
Anything above gets taxed. But the US
has one of the most generous thresholds
in the world. In 2016, the limit was
raised from €200 to $800. Before that,
some 134 million packages entered the
country annually through this
streamlined system. That number has
jumped to nearly 1.4 4 billion units in
2024. This spike is also tied to the
overall boom in global trade. But still
about 90% of all goods coming into the
US are duty-free deminimous imports.
Until April 2025, most of these packages
came from China, usually by air.
Our box has had a long flight and
finally touches down at LAX. Its first
stop in America is a special customs
warehouse. Examining every package that
comes through here would be impossible.
So, customs officers rely on spot
checks. Specially trained dogs sniff out
selected packages for fentinel
precursors.
Sometimes it's the packages weight that
raises suspicion. If it doesn't j with
its description, the box gets flagged
and pulled out for inspection. Flag
packages are scanned by high-tech
machines, opened for manual inspection,
and sometimes even sent to an on-site
chemical lab. And in some cases, custom
officers will also attach electronic
trackers to suspicious boxes to follow
their trail. But given the sheer volume
of packages coming in, only a tiny
fraction ever gets checked. Most of them
are simply waved through, including our
package. It's just been cleared for the
next leg of the trip, which means it has
now officially entered the country. The
master carton is unpacked at a
distribution center. The smaller parcels
are sorted by destination. The next leg
of transport is handled by one of the
regular US delivery firms. Our package
still has a long road ahead. Its next
stop is Mexico.
The vast majority of elicit fentinel is
manufactured here. It's first shipped to
a US address near the Mexican border.
That's when a new link in the supply
chain takes over to handle the border
crossing. The address is a private home.
The tenant is an elderly man. Some
products can't be shipped to Mexico
directly. This is where the man comes
in. He's offering a personal crossber
delivery to make some extra money, a
common side hustle in the border region.
People in Mexico can have their packages
shipped to his US address. Then he
drives them over in his private car. Now
he's on his way to the border with a
couple of boxes in the trunk. The
package from China is one of them. The
border works similar to the airport.
Small boxes are rarely checked. The
cartels are counting on that. The man in
the car looks harmless. He doesn't even
know what's in our package. He's waved
through. The next stop is a distribution
center in the Mexican state of Sinaloa.
Local freight carriers will forward the
packages to the addresses supplied by
their Mexican customers. And so our
package reaches its final destination, a
secret drug lab. This is where it's
opened for the first time.
The Sinalora cartel is one of the most
powerful and violent criminal
organizations in the world. With the
fentinel boom in full swing, they too
have shifted away from heroin production
and gone allin on fentinel.
Inside this old and nondescript house,
two teenagers are working in a makeshift
lab. They're cooking fentinel. They're
not trained chemists. Someone just gave
them a step-by-step tutorial. They open
the package containing the powder from
China and start prepping a new batch.
It's complete routine. The process is
always the same. Making fentinyl is
almost as easy as baking cake. You don't
need much gear either. Our 1 kilo
package yields up to 50,000 doses of
fentinyl. Now, the finished drug heads
back to the US.
It can cross the border in all kinds of
ways. Attached to or even carried inside
the bodies of so-called drug mules or
disguised among regular cargo on some
ordinary delivery van. Smugglers have
hidden fentinel pills in candy bags soon
them into clothing. And in some cases,
drugs are even implanted into pets.
They're simply betting on the fact that
it's impossible for customs to check
every person or item that crosses the
border. More often than not, it's US
citizens who drive the drugs across the
border in their private cars. Sometimes
they come up with clever hidden
compartments like this one.
The car is just minutes away from
crossing.
The driver can already see the custom
officers up ahead with drugniffing dogs
working car to car. He starts to get
nervous, but just as they're coming
toward him, the agents pull away. The
dog needs a break. The stash in his car
goes undetected. The driver exhales.
And just like that, more fentinel made
it into the US.
In 2024 alone, nearly 10 tons of the
drug were seized along the US Mexico
border. But the amount that actually
made it through is by all likelihood
much higher. The fentinel crisis has
also become a geopolitical flash point.
The US accuses China of fueling the
epidemic on purpose. Beijing, for its
part, claims to have cracked down on the
fentinel trade years ago. The real
problem lies in controlling the
precursors. They are much harder to
regulate. Chemical suppliers in China
are using false return labels and
deceptive packaging to conceal their
illegal business with fentinel
precursors. Washington has even talked
about a new opium war. In April 2025,
President Trump signed an executive
order to eliminate duty-free deminimous
imports from China and Hong Kong. He
cited the ongoing health emergency posed
by fentinel trafficking as one of the
reasons for the high tariffs on Chinese
goods. China denies the accusations.
Beijing says the crisis is completely
made in the US and therefore the sole
responsibility of the American
government. Meanwhile, Trump has also
accused Mexico of not doing enough to
crack down on the drug cartels.
Curbing the international fentinel trade
is extremely difficult. The drug has
long made its way beyond North America
and reached places like Europe. Probes
in several German cities have shown that
fentinyl is already being mixed into
street heroin. Getting off fentinel
without medical support is extremely
hard, if not almost impossible.
And as long as it can be produced and
trafficked so easily, the business will
keep booming.